<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Scholars' Lab | Brandon Walsh]]></title>
  <link href="http://walshbr.com/categories/scholars-lab/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://walshbr.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-06-20T19:28:02+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://walshbr.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[{"name"=>"Brandon Walsh", "url"=>"https://twitter.com/mdo", "email"=>"walsh@virginia.edu"}]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Praxis-Oriented Introduction to Digital Pedagogy]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/a-praxis-oriented-introduction-to-digital-pedagogy/"/>
    <updated>2019-05-30T14:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/a-praxis-oriented-introduction-to-digital-pedagogy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Crossposted to the <a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/a-praxis-oriented-introduction-to-digital-pedagogy/">Scholars’ Lab blog</a></em></p>

<p>One thing I’ve realized about the Praxis Program, our year-long, soup-to-nuts introduction to digital humanities for a cohort of doctoral students, is that it changes each year. In my first year here, these changes were a source of anxiety for me. Surely, I thought, there must be a way to systematize the program, to find a format that would be more consistent, and, thus, more sustainable. Over the last two years, however, I’ve come to view these regular tweaks as a strength of the program. Rather than being locked into what we’ve done in the past, we’re committed to re-examining our assumptions and our plans. To illustrate this, I’d like to share an example of a problem we identified and some the ways we tried to address it during the past year.</p>

<p>At the end of every program, we run exit surveys with students and hold debrief conversations among the staff involved. Last year’s discussions brought up an important issue: for all of our talk about how the program is meant to be a curricular intervention in graduate studies and offer on-the-ground, hands-on training in the practical work of digital humanists, we were framing that work almost exclusively in the context of research projects. Our students left without much of a sense of digital pedagogy and what that might mean to them. Even though we encouraged students to document their process as the year went along, our emphasis on producing a digital project suggested that the work of a digital humanist is primarily project development. That might be true for a certain kind of digital humanities work, but it also leaves out so much of what these careers entail. By focusing our work in this way, we, and the students, seemed to be ignoring the strengths of the program as a teaching exercise itself.</p>

<p>Having identified this issue, we decided to spend a month or so of the following year’s program working on a new unit that I would construct on digital pedagogy. In addition to introducing the topic, part of our goal was to create a space for other kinds of outcomes for the year. Rather than having a single group project be the primary takeaway, I wanted our students to start thinking about the year as a portfolio of experiences with lots of different materials they could point to as their own. This addition would also help address one issue we’ve consistently found with the group project - by its very nature, it involves a degree of compromise from each student in the group. If the project feels too far afield from an individual student’s research agenda, it can be difficult to sell them on why they should remain engaged in the collective work. Expanding the range of results for the students also gave us new opportunities to create moments that would speak directly to the students’ individual research interests in a clearer way than we had in past. The whole sequence took place in four sessions.</p>

<p><strong>Session One - Workshopping a Workshop</strong></p>

<p>I called the introductory session to the digital pedagogy unit a “Workshop on Workshops,” a title that I took from a piece <a href="https://zoeleblanc.com/">Zoe LeBlanc</a> and I have coauthored for the forthcoming <em>#DLFTeach Toolkit</em>. That upcoming piece shares the spirit of what follows here, though with a different practical and theoretical framing. Keep an eye out for that volume, which should be dropping soon.</p>

<p>The assignment I gave the students was, over the course of a month, to create the structure for a ninety-minute digital humanities workshop related in some way to their own research interests. They certainly weren’t expected to know everything about the topic, but they could learn just enough to teach - just enough to teach to learn themselves. And, in an attempt to introduce them to a particular form of pedagogy that I tend to traffic in, I asked their workshop be a “low-tech, pencil and paper (ish) digital humanities workshop.” In terms of actual, tangible outcomes, at this stage I just asked they work towards having a blog post-length pitch with the idea, framing, and beginning skeleton for their session. They didn’t need to plan enough to actually give the workshop (yet! stay tuned, dear reader), but I wanted evidence that they had made significant progress in that direction. And the plan was that throughout the month we would workshop their materials together.</p>

<p>I suggested pencil and paper as a constraint by way of a reading we gave the students: “<a href="https://crln.acrl.org/index.php/crlnews/article/view/16833/18427">Beyond Buttonology: Digital Humanities, Digital Pedagogy, and the ACRL Framework</a>” by John E. Russell and Merinda Kaye Hensley. The students read the piece, and we then opened the discussion with this quotation from it:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Knowing how to upload texts into a tool like Voyant does not help researchers think about what texts should be uploaded, how selecting data relates to a research question, or even what constitutes an effective research question.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The challenge for the students was to take seriously the provocation of the article, to get beyond workshops geared towards interfaces and tools (beyond buttonology) and towards concepts and methods. In doing so, I hoped, the students would realize that they could effectively approach and teach complicated digital humanities concepts as newcomers, even if they might be otherwise unfamiliar with the tools that might often be used to address these research questions. Learning about the former would hopefully mean they felt more comfortable exploring, evaluating, and recommending these tools to others. After introducing the concept of buttonology, we reflected on past technology workshops we had attended. What did good teaching look like in those contexts? What did less successful teaching look like? Was buttonology a concept or experience they had encountered before, even if they did not have a name for it?</p>

<p>We then got specific. In order to set the stage for this exploration, I modeled an example workshop for them by giving an introduction to sentiment analysis using pencil and paper. I’ve written about <a href="http://walshbr.com/blog/ways-to-read/">this particular workshop at length</a>, so I won’t fully rehash the approach. Suffice it to say that I introduced the concept of sentiment analysis, asked the students to mark up by hand a passage for positive and negative polarity, and then used the resultant discussion to surface many of the underlying, humanistic issues with the methodology.</p>

<p>I’ve taught versions of this workshop in a number of contexts, but the difference here was that I approached it like something of a supervised laboratory experiment. I gave the workshop as normal, but I also described the theoretical and practical reasons behind my pedagogical choices as they took place in real time. It felt a lot like I was running two workshops simultaneously - the first was an introduction to text analysis, and the second was a higher-level conversation on the pedagogical environment and experience I conducted as I went. After the workshop ended, we took a few minutes to reflect on the teaching together. We talked about the advantages (discussion based, little room for technological failure) and disadvantages (difficult to connect it back to things they could immediately use) of the approach.</p>

<p>This mix of practical experience and theoretical reflection would come to be crucial in the coming months as we continued the exercise. With this initial workshop as a model, I challenged the students to aim for a similar outcome of their own from the unit. To get to that point, the following sessions would walk the students through a series of scaffolded exercises meant to draw them from point A to point Z. The follow-up assignment leading into the next session was for the students to reflect on their own, discipline-specific research interests. The students need only do some soul searching and come in with two or three large interventions that their dissertation projects made or, if they weren’t at that point in their programs yet, that they were interested in exploring as graduate students.</p>

<p><strong>Session Two - General research interests</strong></p>

<p>When we reconvened, we asked questions of each other to learn more about our individual research interests, and we offered some points of connection to larger digital humanities topics. By now the students had begun to gather some sense of the larger field, so they had developed the ability to say things like “You’re interested in textual editing? That reminds me of TEI, which we learned about a couple weeks ago.” They might not have felt prepared to go much deeper, but that was fine at this stage. I just wanted them to get things on the table.</p>

<p>In preparation for our next session, I asked the students to explore <em>Digital Pedagogy in the Humanities: Concepts, Models, and Experiments</em>, a fantastic collection of different activities and statements drawing from a wide variety of different areas. I often suggest the collection as an entry point for people interested in learning about DH but who haven’t found their own clearly defined entry point yet. With an eye to their own stated research interests, I asked them to select one or two sections of the volume to explore at length.</p>

<p><strong>Session Three - General DH interests</strong></p>

<p>In this session, we used the <em>Digital Pedagogy</em> volume as a bridge to help narrow each student’s focus within digital humanities. We went around the table and had each student share what they had explored and how it related to their research interests. We started to broach basic questions of pedagogy as well - what could they imagine being engaging to students about the topic? What would likely be difficult to grasp? How might the students address these issues?</p>

<p>Besides offering each of them a chance to think about their own interests, sharing and workshopping for each other meant that the students were also getting a lot of exposure to areas <em>beyond</em> their own interests. Our fellowship cohorts have six people in them, so they were getting a crash course in five topics outside their own field. This general approach guides much of Praxis - we frequently pair a deep dive into one subject or method with broad exposure to a variety of areas. The follow-up work from this session was to continue to narrow. The students had moved from disciplinary interests to DH areas, and now I wanted them to take the final step. I asked them to think through how they would teach something about this subject area to newcomers.</p>

<p><strong>Session Four - Specific, Teachable DH Workshop Ideas</strong></p>

<p>In the last session, the students shared their specific ideas for introductory digital humanities workshops with the group and offered feedback for one another. I continued to broach pedagogical issues, but the students were also quite good at flagging potential problems for each other. They gave strong feedback and asked good questions of each other:</p>

<ul>
  <li>What were the goals of the session?</li>
  <li>What seemed the most challenging for the instructor? What were potential pitfalls?</li>
  <li>Does the instructor seem to be planning too much?</li>
</ul>

<p>With this feedback in mind, the students had one last chance to re-conceive of their work before delivering what, at the time, felt like their final outcomes. Several of the students wound up posting their workshop ideas to the blog. If you’re interested in seeing what they came up with check out the posts below:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/sounding-scholarship-a-workshop-on-making-your-research-sing/">Sounding Scholarship: A Workshop on Making Your Research Sing</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/string-theory-or-lets-explore-social-networks-with-string/">String Theory, or: Let’s Explore Social Networks with String!</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://scholarslab.lib.virginia.edu/blog/teaching-transcription-and-secretly-metaphysics/">Teaching Transcription (and Secretly Metaphysics)</a></li>
</ul>

<p>A general interest in networks in early American history found its way into a workshop on network analysis using string and rope. An interest in textual criticism lead to a workshop on digital editing and transcription. This certainly isn’t the only or best way to introduce students to digital pedagogy. I’ve already prepared a few changes for next year, including asking students to read more theory and readings to go along with the work they’re developing. But, all in all, I think the unit on pedagogy was a success. We had new conversations that hadn’t been a part of Praxis in the past, and it felt as though the shift towards teaching brought out the voices of students who were quieter at other parts of the process. The students also came away with a professionally legible piece they could add to their portfolios, and I felt they were better able to speak to the pedagogical intervention the program itself was trying to make.</p>

<p>As I had originally conceived it, the unit on digital pedagogy ended there. But it turns out the students were <em>really</em> excited about the work they had done and wanted to actually teach the workshops for a live audience. We wanted to honor that energy, so we unexpectedly gave the digital pedagogy unit a second life in the spring semester. I’ll write a second post that will describe that real-life road-testing soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is Praxis Working On?]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/what-is-praxis-working-on/"/>
    <updated>2019-01-10T07:32:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/what-is-praxis-working-on</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Crossposted to the <a href="http://scholarslab.org/blog/what-is-praxis-working-on">Scholars’ Lab blog</a></em></p>

<p>Well, that’s a wrap. The fall semester is done, and 2019 is getting started. Actually, when I first started drafting this post the <em>previous</em> spring semester had just finished wrapping as well. This post has been sitting in my drafts folder since spring of 2018, so I wanted to try to push this out before another semester flew by.</p>

<p>At the end of the spring 2018 semester, the Praxis students presented reveal.scholarslab.org to an utterly packed house, which meant that the first full cycle of Scholars’ Lab student programs under my watch had taken place. It feels like I just got here, but, as I like to mark milestones, it felt worth reflecting on a few lessons from the last year (and then some). In addition, I’ve found myself often describing a few basic theoretical and practical tensions at the heart of our fellowship programs to anyone who is interested in what we do, so it seems worth writing down my thoughts on them in a wider, more public forum. This post, then, will aim to do both of those things by offering a bit of a glimpse into the history of one of our programs and the thinking behind it. In particular, I’ll talk about the line we try to walk between student-centered learning and project-centered learning. I’ll be talking about what Praxis works on each year and how we go about picking that project. Because, frankly, the questions about our programs that I’ve gotten most often over the course of the last year are “what are they?” and “what are they working on?”</p>

<p>Some background and practical considerations. The Praxis Program is just one of our fellowship programs each year, but, as it serves more students than our programs, I think it’s safe to say that it takes up the most mental energy of everyone in the lab. Each year, we take six humanities students from various departments around the University (this year we have our first Architecture School student!) and offer them a soup-to-nuts introduction to digital humanities work. The fellowship asks for about ten hours of attention from the students each week in the form of a weekly meeting or two and collaborative work in a number of forms. The students are funded to participate in it by way of reducing their teaching obligations for the year - the students get time to learn and grow together as a result of the reduced course load. You can read more about the program on <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/about/">the project website</a>, <a href="http://www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de/conference/programme/abstracts/realigning-digital-humanities-training-the-praxis-program-at-the-scholars-lab.1.html">the DH abstract for the poster the team presented when the project first launched</a>, or in this <a href="http://scholarslab.org/grad-student-research/announcing-the-praxis-program/">introductory post by Bethany Nowviskie</a>. The program draws together several strands of pedagogical theory, a sampling of which might include Paulo Freire’s <em>Pedagogy of the Oppressed</em>, the <a href="http://cdh.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/">UCLA Student Collaborator’s Bill of Rights</a>, or many of the writings of bell hooks.</p>

<p>We’ve published a pair of charters outlining the pedagogical obligations we feel towards our students, both in the <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/praxis-program-charter">Praxis program</a> and in <a href="http://scholarslab.org/student-programs-charter/">our programs more generally</a>. (These charters didn’t exist when I first drafted this post in the spring of 2018. That’s one benefit of waiting seven months to finalize a post!) Check those documents out for general statements about our belief in public, process-driven pedagogy. But those statements won’t illuminate much about the day-to-day of what life is like for our students in our programs. Nor will they necessarily illuminate much about the logistics of how we carry out a fellowship year. So I thought I would share a little more about those specifics - what our students work on and how they get there. After all, the theory informs the doing, and the writing of those documents helped shape our programs this year.</p>

<p>One thing I’ve been thinking a lot about this year is the primary vehicle by which we facilitate the learning process in the Praxis program - the project. I usually put it this way: Praxis is a year-long fellowship that has a distinctive shift in feel between the fall and spring semesters. In the fall, there is still a fair amount of the Scholars’ Lab staff in the front of the class leading seminars or giving workshops to the students, as you might expect from a class where they will be learning a lot of digital methods. But we also share a range of strategies and techniques that aim to give a high-level look at all the different components of digital work - intellectual property, project scoping and management, collaboration planning, and way more (you can check out the common curriculum <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/curriculum/">here</a>). Most importantly, we help them think about what they’ll be doing together during the year: we help them design and scope a project that they’ll be working on in the spring, when we shift to much more of a hands-on, side-by-side, lab approach to the learning experience. While we still think a lot in the spring, our day-to-day work is mostly taken up working together to make the thing happen. We try to give the students power over the process all year long, but this is really evident in the spring when we put them in charge as much as possible.</p>

<p>Folks interested in Praxis often ask what the students are working on because, at the end of the day, people know that we want them to build <em>something</em>. But how they get to it has changed significantly over time. In <a href="http://nowviskie.org/2011/praxis-and-prism/">another post</a> by Nowviskie, she mentions that “It’s just too much to ask that students new to digital humanities work invent a meaningful project from whole cloth on Day 1 of the program — especially one that, we hope, will make a meaningful intervention in the current scene of DH research and practice.”</p>

<p>I think it’s worth sharing a little Praxis history here. (I should say at the outset of this discussion that, while I was a student in the second cohort of the program, I was never really privy to the pedagogical conversations that drove the fellowship. So take all of these observations from the outside with a grain of salt, except for the last year or so where I am happy to take any blame.) The compromise in the first few years was to give the students a piece of vaporware or a project already in progress and, within those restrictions, ask the students to make this kernel of an idea their own and to develop their own intellectual contribution based on it. The first Praxis cohort developed <a href="http://prism.scholarslab.org">Prism</a>, a digital version of a vaporware experiment in collaborative textual analysis and visualization developed by Nowviskie and SpecLab. The second cohort extended Prism, adding in new features based on their own interests and priorities, with the goal of taking the project from a proof of concept to a tool that was more open and usable. Accordingly, Prism has seen significant uptake, particularly in K-12 classrooms as a pedagogical tool for teaching a variety of reading and interpretive skills.</p>

<p>In its third year, the program took a similar approach to developing a project - the staff tasked the Praxis cohort with developing a new version of <a href="http://ivanhoe.scholarslab.org/">Ivanhoe</a>, another older Scholars’ Lab project that was an exercise in collaborative interpretation and literary intervention, that would run as a WordPress theme. The following year, the fourth cohort of students redesigned Ivanhoe further to allow multimedia contributions.</p>

<p>So, in one sense, the first four years of the Praxis program were heavily directed - the core project was given, but the intellectual framing, stakes, and intervention itself were left to the students. Because of this, the students were saved the difficult task of making a from-scratch contribution to a field they were just learning for the first time. The students still maintained ownership of the project, but the initial guidance meant that the projects were able to go quite far for student projects. Each project ran on a two-year cycle, which meant that one cohort was tasked with the heavy lifting of developing a first pass at the digital project while the next would inherit the intellectual weight of conversations they hadn’t participated in. Each cohort got different glimpses of the lifecycle of a digital project.</p>

<p>The next three years were even more student-directed. The students still were given wide latitude over the kinds of skills they took away and the nature of the project that developed at the end, but different productive constraints were used to guide the work of the group. The staff stepped back a bit more in years five and six of the program and did not explicitly give a project to the students. Rather than being given an explicit project, the students were given an idea or topic. In each case, the students were told to think about the concept of time and develop a project that would intervene in our understanding of it. Naturally, the slightly more free-form approach meant that the students had the leeway to take wildly different approaches. The fifth cohort developed <a href="http://clockwork.scholarslab.org/">ClockWork</a>, which used sonification to grapple with the monetary measurements of time. The sixth cohort took time as encouragement to think about social media as the best representation of the now, and these investigations led them to think about the <a href="http://dashamerikan.scholarslab.org">social media ecologies of the Kardashian family</a>. In the seventh year, my first in charge of the program, we stepped back even more, leaving off the time prompt for the students. We came in with a light plan but really followed student interests where they wanted to go, giving broad freedom over the direction of the program and the project. The result was <a href="http://reveal.scholarslab.org/">UVA Reveal: Augmenting the University</a>, a project that used augmented reality to layer contextual information onto public spaces to challenge public narratives of contested spaces. Ironically, even though time wasn’t the students’ focus, the project still deeply engaged in questions of the past, the present, and the stories we tell ourselves about both.</p>

<p>For the eighth, current year of the program we’ve instituted some significant changes to things that I will write more about in the future. But relevant to this discussion about freedom vs. constraint is that we returned somewhat to the roots of the program, providing the students with a fairly well defined kernel of an idea to make their own and implement in their own way. Students this year are working with the library’s Director of Information Policy to develop a project that engages with the ramifications of January 1st, 2019, when new works entered the public domain for the first time since the passage of the 1998 Sonny Bono Copyright Extension Act. I can go on about how excited I am for it, but I’d prefer for the students to frame the intervention themselves when they’re ready to do so. Keep an eye out for those insights!</p>

<p>Therefore, in answer to the question “What is Praxis working on?” I’d say: the students have worked on many different types of things over the years.</p>

<p>I think, however, that people ask what we’re engaged with presently not just to get a sense of the final product, but also in an attempt to better understand our process. Because no matter how public and transparent we try to be, the program is always happening for a small group of students behind doors that, if not closed, are cracked only slightly (we’re a library after all).</p>

<p>In that case, I have a slightly more boring answer to the question that I think really gets at the heart of the program.</p>

<p>What is Praxis working on?</p>

<p>We’re working on it.</p>

<p>The truth is we could have the students work on pretty much anything. The discussions would change, and the interventions into the scholarly conversations might be more or less incisive. But the built project is only part of the equation for us. And as <a href="http://scholarslab.org/charter/">the Scholars’ Lab charter</a> states, the development of our people is at least as important as the projects or products themselves. The <em>thing</em> the students work on is less important than what that object can do in the service of the larger group. Our real aim is to build up the students as confident, conversant scholar-practitioners of digital method.</p>

<p>Praxis can be difficult to describe because it changes every year, and that’s by design. The content of the project changes, sure, and the students necessarily change. But the staff also changes - the lab has had a lot of turnover since Praxis began. I’m now the third or fourth person to take charge of Praxis, and we all have different ways of running things and conceptualizing the program. Rather than think of the program as a search for the perfect approach to project-based pedagogy, in the last year I’ve really come to see its evolving nature as a strength. When I’m asked what is Praxis working on, I’m led to think about how we’re constantly trying to reshape our fundamental assumptions, re-evaluating the process, and making changes based on the needs of our students. The staff are always working on the fellowship program itself.</p>

<p>Because process is everything. <em>How</em> we have students approach the work can really set the students up for success for failure-even more than the nature of the project itself. In the Scholars’ Lab, we’re committed to putting the students in charge of their education. But doing so can take a lot of different shapes, and Praxis has led to a lot of questions for me in the last year - questions that have been going round in my head all year and that have drifted outwards in this post. What are our limits at the lab in how design the student experience? How free can we be? How constrained? I’ve taken to jokingly describing the Praxis program as a riff on the tagline of the old MTV show <em>Real World</em> - “seven strangers picked to live in a house.” Except, in our case, we have six strangers picked to work on a project together. Are we setting them up for drama worthy of reality TV or for transformative learning experiences?</p>

<p>What is Praxis working on right now?</p>

<p>We’re working on being better. More on that soon!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Praxis and Scale: On The Virtue of Small]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/praxis-and-scale-on-the-virtue-of-small/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-15T09:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/praxis-and-scale-on-the-virtue-of-small</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The following is a version of my talk for DH2018 that will be given as a part of a roundtable on Digital Humanities Pedagogy and Praxis. Participants on the panel responded to a <a href="http://praxis-network.org/dh2018/">CFP</a> marking five years since we launched the <a href="http://praxis-network.org/">Praxis Network</a>.</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/praxis-and-scale/1.jpeg" alt="title slide" /></p>

<p>I am Brandon Walsh, the Head of Graduate Programs at the Scholars’ Lab in the University of Virginia Library in the United States. Today I want to talk about a tension I see in DH pedagogy between the hands-on, student-driven instruction that we’re discussing here as part of the Praxis Network and the scale at which we can offer it. Can we take what started small and scale it up in an ethical and informed way? In particular, I want to suggest that “small” investments in pedagogy driven by students are worth it, that we should resist uncritical calls to scale up the reach of our praxis, and that we can best measure the growth of our programs by the degree to which our students are empowered to become engaged, generous teachers in their own right.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/praxis-and-scale/2.jpeg" alt="praxis program summary" /></p>

<p>My own local context for this talk is the Scholars’ Lab’s <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/">Praxis Program</a>, which offers a targeted digital humanities injection during the early years of a student’s graduate work. In the Praxis Program each year, staff and faculty work alongside a student cohort to theorize a new digital intervention and to train the students to implement it themselves. We shift from a series of workshops and discussions in the fall semester to a lab model in the spring, from the staff in front of the room to all of us working together to get a thing done. Funding for the program comes from the library in the form of teaching releases for the students, and I’m happy to talk more about these practical details in the Q&amp;A. The program aims to equip graduate students with the skills and ethos necessary to thrive when carrying out collaborative, open work that might happen on or off the tenure track, and, drawing upon the pedagogical theories of Cathy Davidson, Paolo Freire, Bethany Nowviskie, and others, we do this by putting the students in charge, allowing them as much as possible to decide what they work on and how they’ll work on it.</p>

<p>This panel invites us to reflect on how student programs like these have changed in the past several years, on their triumphs and difficulties. Now in its seventh year, we measure the Praxis Program’s success by a number of metrics - exit interviews, job placements, future awards received by our alumni, and publications.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/praxis-and-scale/3.jpeg" alt="praxis projects slide" /></p>

<p>We’ve assembled a <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/projects">series of projects</a> of varying shapes and sizes, conceived and developed by the students themselves and with various afterlives, and a host of alumni who have gone on to build on their time with us. But we sometimes get questions or comments about the program’s scale.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/praxis-and-scale/4.jpeg" alt="scale slide with image of empty chairs" /></p>

<p>Each cohort consists of six students. Pretty small compared to a traditional course that might engage a single instructor, and, what’s more, this program draws in virtually all of our staff at one time or another. That is a significant investment of resources in a small group of students each year. Over the years we’ve been asked about the limits of the model from a number of people, inside and outside UVA. Can we have a second cohort of students each year? Could we take the model and grow it?</p>

<p>They’re reasonable asks, but they raise a number of issues for me that I hope might be useful for any student program. The first is simple – can a model like this grow? Although we have some <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/resources/">recurring units, lessons, and resources</a> each year, the student-driven nature of the Praxis Program requires us to embrace the unexpected. <a href="http://reveal.scholarslab.org/">This last year</a>, for example, we started out with one idea but reversed course and rebuilt the curriculum based on the unfolding interests of our students.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/praxis-and-scale/5.jpeg" alt="image of Praxis resources and curriculum published online" /></p>

<p>This requires a serious commitment of time and resources - it can be difficult to predict exactly which staff members will be the primary points of contact for the project, and responsibilities might change unexpectedly. There is also a question of capacity. We are limited in the number of students that we can maintain at any one time and still carry out our other obligations as a library unit. I should note here that there are powerful examples of people doing this kind of engaged student work on a large scale - the <a href="https://www.hastac.org/groups/hastac-futureed">#FutureEd initiative</a> by Davidson and others is a clear example, and instructors in the sciences are often already working at a much larger scale when they try to implement similar approaches in their lecture courses. Numbers might be part of a necessary approach to your own critically engaged pedagogy.</p>

<p>Another question - should it grow? Perhaps rather than expanding a single working model, resources might be better served in other areas, other programs, other people - more on that in a moment. For our group, at least, keeping a smaller program that centers project-based education is a strategic investment in the individual as a meaningful point of intervention. The core of our work, more than any digital project, is the people, who we try empower to act as DH professionals and pay their lessons forward from day one. Far from limiting our impact, I think that deliberately staying small attempts to do more with less, to invest in the futures of these students as they become teachers themselves. We believe in the grassroots impact these young people can have on the field and on their communities.</p>

<p>And finally - how should it grow? Most importantly, to me at least, is that we continue to develop educational experiences that are as equitable and just as possible. In my experience, conversations around scale aren’t usually met with offers for more resources. And we should not let calls to grow tempt us into uncritically adopting volunteer labor or unpaid internships. <a href="http://cdh.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/">UCLA’s Student Collaborator’s Bill of Rights</a> is a touchstone here. Students might be willing to volunteer their time with you for the sake of the experience, but our position is that we should resist those offers. There is plenty of evidence to suggest that allowing such unpaid labor reinforces socioeconomic and racial disparities in the workforce. We try not to grow beyond our ability to fund our students.</p>

<p>I want to pause momentarily to recognize that this is a fairly privileged conversation. The Scholars’ Lab programs are in the fortunate position to be well funded at the time of this writing, and (even at my own institution) there are many units and individual people tasked with raising programs from the ground on little to no funding. I’m sure there are some of you in the room in that same position. My colleagues and I are fortunate. Ours is not the only way to shape a program, and it’s certainly not the best one for every institutional context. I hope, however, that this conversation might offer those of you making difficult decisions about resources a model – or, at least, a series of ideas – to consider. You don’t need an extensive reach or a robust cohort of students to make something meaningful happen. If you can fund one student – that is worth doing. Embrace the fact that you can engage that one person in the important work of developing and growing your program. Do what you can with what you can, but, again, we should collectively resist calls to grow student programs beyond our capacity to resource and sustain them.</p>

<p>I think a lot about the disparate amounts of privilege some of our students enjoy, and much of our effort is spent trying to scale our impact in ways that broaden access even though we can’t afford a deep dive with many students. This means offering a diverse range of ways in for students, with other <a href="http://scholarslab.org/graduate-fellowships/">opportunities</a> for engaging our community that might be more targeted and more sustainable. It also means engaging alumni of the Praxis Program in our other initiatives, folding their strengths into our pool of resources and giving them opportunities to explore themselves as teachers. We try to engage these students who have been able to access our resources, time, and knowledge in helping their colleagues who might not have benefited from the same.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/praxis-and-scale/6.jpeg" alt="image of LAMI program fellows" /></p>

<p>Since the Praxis Program’s inception, for example, we have partnered with our campus’s version of the <a href="https://graddiversity.virginia.edu/U.Va.LAMI">Leadership Alliance Mellon Initiative (LAMI)</a> to pilot a complimentary program in DH and library research methods for undergraduates from underrepresented communities with the assistance of our Praxis alumni. The undergraduates taking part in this program are thinking about graduate school, and our contribution is to give them just a taste of what research at that level might look like for them. Our Praxis alumni lead a workshop for them, participate in discussions, and also show what the next phase of life after undergraduate can look like.</p>

<p>I’ve talked a bit about our past and present. A single thought on the future of our programs it would be this - I think it is incumbent upon us to turn our work outwards and think about the impact our students can have on a broader community beyond our institution - that’s where the Scholars’ Lab has been heading, and I’d like to continue in that direction. In the direction of out rather than in.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/praxis-and-scale/7.jpeg" alt="List of student workshops at Washington and Lee" /></p>

<p>One way in which we’ve tried to do this is to work more closely with institutions in the region. We’ve partnered with Washington and Lee for a few years now to engage students as guest DH workshop leaders on their campus, and we’re soon hoping to expand to University of Richmond as well. We ask our students to blog about these workshops, and we have been accumulating a <a href="https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/blog/category/uva-collaboration/">list of these resources</a> for others to learn from or build upon. Similarly, I would like to extend the work of our students to the local Charlottesville community, <a href="https://news.library.virginia.edu/2018/06/18/library-receives-grant-from-lyrasis-for-digital-collecting-in-times-of-crisis/">something the Lab has been increasingly engaged in</a>, but I would like us to be more deliberate about incorporating students as we do so. We can continue to empower student research but do so as part of the Lab’s mission of promoting access, sharing resources, and advancing social justice.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/praxis-and-scale/8.jpeg" alt="Title slide redone" /></p>

<p>If I have one point today point it is this - there are limits to the number of deep dives you can take. But they can serve as excellent starting points for other schemes - you can do a lot with a little. Our former director, Bethany Nowviskie, once used the phrase “too small to fail” to describe our approach to graduate education. Small can still have a big impact. At the Scholars’ Lab, I’d like our own particular brand of small to be public, engaged, and local, empowering students who feel confident but also compelled to give back to their peers, students, and neighborhoods. Weighing ourselves in this way, by the degree to which we help to democratize and provide access to these sorts of methods, questions, and technologies ultimately feels more meaningful than doing so by the number of students we reach.</p>

<p>References and Further Reading</p>

<ul>
  <li>A Student Collaborators’ Bill of Rights. University of California Los Angeles Center for Digital Humanities. <a href="http://cdh.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/">http://cdh.ucla.edu/news/a-student-collaborators-bill-of-rights/</a></li>
  <li>#FutureEd. Humanities, Arts, Science, and Technology Alliance and Collaboratory. <a href="https://www.hastac.org/initiatives/futureed">https://www.hastac.org/initiatives/futureed</a></li>
  <li>Davidson, C. (2017). The New Education: How to Revolutionize the University to Prepare Students for a World In Flux. New York, NY: Basic Books.</li>
  <li>Freire, P. (1970). Pedagogy of the Oppressed. New York, NY: Bloomsbury Academic.</li>
  <li>Nowviskie, B. (2011). “Praxis and Prism.” <a href="http://nowviskie.org/2011/praxis-and-prism/">http://nowviskie.org/2011/praxis-and-prism/</a>
———. (2012). “Too Small To Fail.” <a href="http://nowviskie.org/2012/too-small-to-fail/">http://nowviskie.org/2012/too-small-to-fail/</a></li>
  <li>Rogers, K. (2015). “Humanities Unbound: Supporting Careers and Scholarship Beyond the Tenure Track.” Digital Humanities Quarterly 9.1.</li>
  <li>The Praxis Program. University of Virginia Library’s Scholars’ Lab. <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org">http://praxis.scholarslab.org</a>.</li>
  <li>The Praxis Network. University of Virginia Library’s Scholars’ Lab. <a href="http://praxis-network.org/">http://praxis-network.org/</a>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In, Out, Across, With: Collaborative Education and Digital Humanities (Job Talk for Scholars' Lab)]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/in-out-across-with/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-02T09:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/in-out-across-with</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>[Crossposted on the <a href="https://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/blog/2017/03/06/in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities-job-talk-for-scholars-lab/">WLUDH blog</a> and the <a href="http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities-job-talk-for-head-of-graduate-programs/">Scholars’ Lab blog</a>]</em></p>

<p>I’ve accepted a new position as the <a href="http://scholarslab.org/uncategorized/brandon-walsh-is-our-new-head-of-graduate-programs-starting-april-24-2017/">Head of Graduate Programs in the Scholars’ Lab</a>, and I’ll be transitioning into that role over the next few weeks! As a part of the interview process, we had to give a job talk. While putting together this presentation, I was lucky enough to have past examples to work from (as you’ll be able to tell, if you check out this past <a href="http://literaturegeek.com/2016/02/28/DHjobtalk">job talk</a> by Amanda Visconti). Since my new position will involve helping graduate students through the process of applying for positions like these, it only feels right that I should post my own job talk as well as a few words on the thinking that went into it. Blemishes, jokes, and all, hopefully these materials will help someone in the future find a way in, just as the example of others did for me. And if you’re looking for more, Visconti has a great list of other examples linked from her <a href="http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/disrupt-the-humanities-managing-director-job-talk/">more recent job talk</a> for the Scholars’ Lab.</p>

<p>For the presentation, I was asked to respond to this prompt:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What does a student (from undergraduate to doctoral levels) need to learn or experience in order to add “DH” to his or her skill set?  Is that an end or a means of graduate education?  Can short-term digital assignments in discipline-specific courses go beyond “teaching with technology”?  Why not refer everyone to online tutorials?  Are there risks for doctoral students or the untenured in undertaking digital projects?  Drawing on your own experience, and offering examples or demonstrations of digital research projects, pedagogical approaches, or initiatives or organizations that you admire, make a case for a vision of collaborative education in advanced digital scholarship in the arts and humanities.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I felt that each question could be a presentation all its own, and I had strong opinions about each one. Dealing with all of them seemed like a tall order. I decided to spend the presentation close reading and deconstructing that first sentence, taking apart the idea that education and/or digital humanities could be thought of in terms of lists of skills at all. Along the way, my plan was to dip into the other questions as able, but I also assumed that I would have plenty of time during the interview day to give my thoughts on them. I also wanted to try to give as honest a sense as possible of the way I approach teaching and mentoring. For me, it’s all about people and giving them the care that they need. In conveying that, I hoped, I would give the sort of vision the prompt was asking for. I also tried to sprinkle references to the past and present of the Scholars’ Lab programs to ground the content of the talk. When I mention potential career options in the body of the talk, I am talking about specific alumni who came through the fellowship programs. And when I mention graduate fellows potentially publishing on their work with the Twitter API, well, <a href="http://scholarslab.org/uncategorized/working-with-an-archive-of-the-now/">that’s not hypothetical either</a>.</p>

<p>So below find the lightly edited text of the talk I gave at the Scholars’ Lab - “In, Out, Across, With: Collaborative Education and Digital Humanities.” I’ve only substantively  modified one piece - swapping out one example for another.</p>

<p>And a final note on delivery: I have heard plenty of people argue over whether it is better to read a written talk or deliver one from notes. My own sense is that the latter is far more common for digital humanities talks. I have seen both fantastic read talks and amazing extemporaneous performances, just as I have seen terrible versions of each. My own approach is, increasingly, to write a talk but deliver that talk more or less from memory. In this case, I had a pretty long commute to work, so I recorded myself reading the talk and listened to it a lot to get the ideas in my head. When I gave the presentation, I had the written version in front of me for reference, but I was mostly moving through my own sense of how it all fit together in real time (and trying to avoid looking at the paper). My hope is that this gave me the best of both worlds and resulted in a structured but engaging performance. Your mileage may vary!</p>

<h2 id="in-out-across-with-collaborative-education-and-digital-humanities">In, Out, Across, With: Collaborative Education and Digital Humanities</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide01.jpg" alt="Title slide" /> It’s always a treat to be able to talk with the members of the UVA Library community, and I am very grateful to be here. For those of you that don’t know me, I am Brandon Walsh, Mellon Digital Humanities Fellow and Visiting Assistant Professor of English at Washington and Lee University. The last time I was here, I gave a talk that had almost exclusively animal memes for slides. I can’t promise the same robust Internet culture in this talk, but talk to me after and I can hook you up. I swear I’ve still got it.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide02.jpg" alt="Zotero slide" /> In the spirit of Amanda Visconti, the resources that went into this talk (and a number of foundational materials on the subject) can all be found in a Zotero collection at the <a href="https://www.zotero.org/bmw9t/items/collectionKey/9KAAWQGG">above link</a>. I’ll name check any that are especially relevant, but hopefully this set of materials will allow the thoughts in the talk to flower outwards for any who are interested in seeing its origins and echoes in the work of others.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide03.jpg" alt="Thank you slide" /> And a final prefatory note: no person works, thinks or learns alone, so here are the names of the people in my talk whose thinking I touch upon as well as just some – but not all – of my colleagues at W&amp;L who collaborate on the projects I mention. Top tier consists of people I cite or mention, second tier is for institutions or publications important to discussion, and final tier is for direct collaborators on this work.</p>

<p>Today I want to talk to you about how best to champion the people involved in collaborative education in digital research. I especially want to talk about students. And when I mention “students” throughout this talk, I will mostly be speaking in the context of graduate students. But most of what I discuss will be broadly applicable to all newcomers to digital research. My talk is an exhortation to find ways to elevate the voices of people in positions like these to be contributors to professional and institutional conversations from day one and to empower them to define the methods and the outcomes of the digital humanities that we teach. This means taking seriously the messy, fraught, and emotional process of guiding students through digital humanities methods, research, and careers. It means advocating for the legibility of this digital work as a key component of their professional development. And it means enmeshing these voices in the broader network around them, the local context that they draw upon for support and that they can enrich in turn. I believe it is the mission of the Head of Graduate Programs to build up this community and facilitate these networks, to incorporate those who might feel like outsiders to the work that we do. Doing so enriches and enlivens our communities and builds a better and more diverse research and teaching agenda. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide04.jpg" alt="Title Slide 2" /> This talk is titled “In, Out, Across, With: Collaborative Education and Digital Humanities,” and I’ll really be focusing on the prepositions of my title as a metaphor for the nature of this sort of position. I see this role as one of connection and relation. The talk runs about 24 minutes, so we should have plenty of time to talk.</p>

<p>When discussing digital humanities education, it is tempting to first and foremost discuss what, exactly, it is that you will be teaching. What should the students walk away knowing? To some extent, just as there is more than one way to make breakfast, you could devise numerous baseline curricula. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide05.jpg" alt="W&amp;L Skills" /></p>

<p>This is what we came up with at Washington and Lee for students in our <a href="http://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/initiatives/undergraduate-fellowship/">undergraduate digital humanities fellowship program</a>. We tried to hit a number of kinds of skills that a practicing digital humanist might need. It’s by no means exhaustive, but the list is a way to start. We don’t expect one person to come away knowing everything, so instead we aim for students to have an introduction to a wide variety of technologies by the end of a semester or year. They’ll encounter some technologies applicable to project management, some to front-end design, as well as a variety of programming concepts broadly applicable to a variety of situations. Lists like this give some targets to hit. But still, even as someone who helped put this list together, it makes me worry a bit. I can imagine younger me being afraid of it! It’s easy for us to forget what it was like to be new, to be a beginner, to be learning for the first time, but I’d like to return us to that frame of thinking. I think we should approach lists like these with care, because they can be intimidating for the newcomer. So in my talk today I want to argue against lists of skills as ways of thinking.</p>

<p>I don’t mean to suggest that programs need no curriculum, nor do I mean to suggest that no skills are necessary to be a digital humanist. But I would caution against focusing too much on the skills that one should have at the end of a program, particularly when talking about people who haven’t yet begun to learn. I would wager that many people on the outside looking in think of DH in the same way: it’s a big list of unknowns. I’d like to get away from that.</p>

<p>Templates like this are important for developing courses, fellowship, and degree-granting programs, but I worry that the goodwill in them might all too easily seem like a form of gatekeeping to a new student. It is easy to imagine telling a student that “you have to learn GitHub before you can work on this project.” It’s just a short jump from this to a likely student response - “ah sorry - I don’t know that yet.” And from there I can all too easily imagine the common refrain that you hear from students of all levels - “If I can’t get that, then it’s because I’m not a technology person.” From there - “Digital humanities must not be for me.”</p>

<p>Instead of building our curricula out of as-yet-unknown tool chains, I want to float, today, a vision of DH education as an introduction to a series of professional practices. Lists of skills might be ends but I fear they might foreclose beginnings. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide06.jpg" alt="SCI Slide" /> Instead, I will float something more in line with that of the Scholarly Communication Institute (held here at UVA for a time), which outlined what they saw as the needs of graduate and professional students in the digital age. I’ll particularly draw upon their first point here (last of my slides with tons of text, I swear): graduate students need training in “collaborative modes of knowledge production and sharing.”</p>

<p>I want to think about teaching DH as introducing a process of discovery that collapses hierarchies between expert and newcomer: that’s a way to start. This sort of framing offers digital humanities not as a series of methods one does or does not know, but, rather, as a process that a group can engage in together. Do they learn methods and skills in the process? Of course! Anyone who has taken part in the sort of collaborative group projects undertaken by the Scholars’ Lab comes away knowing more than they came in with. But I want to continue thinking about process and, in particular, how that process can be more inclusive and more engaging. By empowering students to choose what they want to learn and how they want to learn it, we can help to expand the reach of our work and better serve our students as mentors and collaborators. There are a few different in ways in which I see this as taking place, and they’ll form the roadmap for the rest of the talk. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide07.jpg" alt="Roadmap Slide" /> Apologies - this looks like the sort of slide you would get at a business retreat. All the same - we need to adapt and develop new professional opportunities for our students at the same time that we plan flexible outcomes for our educational programs. These approaches are meant to serve increasingly diverse professional needs in a changing job market, and they need to be matched by deepening support at the institutional level.</p>

<p>So to begin. One of our jobs as mentors is to encourage students to seek out professionally legible opportunities early on in their careers, and as shapers of educational programs we can go further and create new possibilities for them. At W&amp;L, we have been <a href="https://github.com/wludh/research-one-collab">collaborating with the Scholars’ Lab</a> to bring UVA graduate students to teach short-form workshops on digital research in W&amp;L classrooms. Funded opportunities like this one can help students professionalize in new ways and in new contexts while paying it forward to the nearby community. A similar initiative at W&amp;L that I’ve been working on has our own library faculty and undergraduate fellows visiting local high schools to speak with advanced AP computer science students about how their own programming work can apply to humanities disciplines. I’m happy to talk more about these in Q&amp;A.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide08.jpg" alt="Student slide" /> We also have our student collaborators present at conferences, both on their own work and on work they have done with faculty members, both independently and as co-presenters. Here is Abdur, one of our undergraduate Mellon DH fellows, talking about the writing he does for his thesis and how it is enriched by and different from the writing he does in digital humanities contexts at the Bucknell Digital Scholarship Conference last fall. While this sort of thing is standard for graduate students, it’s pretty powerful for an undergraduate to present on research in this way. Learning that it’s OK to fail in public can be deeply empowering, and opportunities like these encourage our students to think about themselves as valuable contributors to ongoing conversations long before they might otherwise feel comfortable doing so.</p>

<p>But teaching opportunities and conferences are not the only ways to get student voices out there. I think there are ways of engaging student voices earlier, at home, in ways that can fit more situations. We can encourage students to engage in professional conversations by developing flexible outcomes in which we are equal participants. One approach to this with which I have been experimenting is group writing, which I think is undervalued as a taught skill and possible approach to DH pedagogy. An example: when a history faculty member at W&amp;L approached the library (and by extension, me) for support in supplementing an extant history course with a component about digital text analysis, we could have agreed to offer a series of one-off workshops and be done with it. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide09.jpg" alt="Gitbook slide" /> Instead, this faculty member – Professor Sarah Horowitz – and I decided to collaborate on a more extensive project together, producing <a href="http://www.walshbr.com/textanalysiscoursebook">Introduction to Text Analysis: A Coursebook</a>. The idea was to put the materials for the workshops together ahead of time, in collaboration, and to narrativize them into a set of lessons that would persist beyond a single semester as a kind of publication. The pedagogical labor that we put into reshaping her course could become, in some sense, professionally legible as a series of course modules that others could use beyond the term. So for the book, we co-authored a series of units on text analysis and gave feedback on each other’s work, editing and reviewing as well as reconfiguring them for the context of the course. Professor Horowitz provided more of the discipline-specific material that I could not, and I provided the materials more specific to the theories and methods of text analysis. Neither one of us could have written the book without the other.</p>

<p>Professor Horowitz was, in effect, a student in this moment. She was also a teacher and researcher. She was learning at the same time that she produced original scholarly contributions. Even as we worked together, for me this collaborative writing project was also a pedagogical experiment that drew upon the examples of <a href="https://openamlit.pressbooks.com/">Robin DeRosa</a>, <a href="http://workbook.craftingdigitalhistory.ca/">Shawn Graham</a>, and <a href="https://www.hastac.org/collections/field-notes-21st-century-literacies">Cathy Davidson</a>, in particular. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide10.jpg" alt="Davidson Slide" /> Davidson taught a graduate course on “21st Century Literacies” where each of her students wrote a chapter that was then collected and published as an open-access book. For us as for Davidson, the process of knowing, the process of uncovering is something that happens together. In public. And it’s documented so that others can benefit. Our teaching labor could become visible and professionally legible, as could the labor that Professor Horowitz put into learning new research skills. As she adapts and tries out ideas, and as we coalesce them into a whole, the writing product is both the means and the end of an introduction to digital humanities.</p>

<p>Professor Horowitz also wanted to learn technical skills herself, and she learned quite a lot through the writing process. Rather than sitting through lectures or being directed to online tutorials by me, I thought she would learn better by engaging with and shaping the material directly. Her course and my materials would be better for it, as she would be helping to bind my lectures and workshops to her course material. The process would also require her to engage with a list of technologies for digital publishing. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide11.jpg" alt="Gitbook Toolchain Slide" /> Beyond the text analysis materials and concepts, the process exposed her to a lot of technologies: command line, Markdown, Git for version control, GitHub for project management. In the process of writing this document, in fact, she covered most of the same curriculum as our undergraduate DH fellows. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide12.jpg" alt="Fellows Skills Slide" /> She’s learning these things as we work together to produce course materials, but, importantly, the technical skills aren’t the focus of the work together. It’s a writing project! Rather than presenting the skills as ends in themselves, they were the means by which we were publishing a thing. They were immediately useful. And I think displacing the technology is helpful: it means that the outcomes and parameters for success are not based in the technology itself but, rather, in the thinking about and use of those methods. We also used a <a href="https://www.gitbook.com">particular platform</a> that allowed Professor Horowitz to engage with these technologies in a light way so that they would not overwhelm our work – I’m happy to discuss more in the time after if you’re interested.</p>

<p>This to say: the outcomes of such collaborative educations can be shaped to a variety of different settings and types of students. Take another model, <a href="https://digitalfellows.commons.gc.cuny.edu/">CUNY’s Graduate Center Digital Fellows program</a>, whose students develop open tutorials on digital tools. Learning from this example, rather than simply direct students or colleagues towards online tutorials like these, why not have them write their own documents, legible for their own positions, that synthesize and remix the materials that they already have found? <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide13.jpg" alt="Programming Historian Slide" /> The learning process becomes something productive in this framing. I can imagine, for example, directing collaboratively authored materials by students like these towards something like <a href="https://programminghistorian.org/">The Programming Historian</a>. If you’re not familiar, The Programming Historian offers a variety of lessons on digital humanities methods, and they only require an outline as a pitch to their editorial team, not a whole written publication ready to go. Your graduate students could, say, work with the Twitter API over the course of a semester, blog about the research outcomes, and then pitch a tutorial to The Programming Historian on the API as a result of their work. It’s much easier to motivate yourselves to write something if you know that the publication has already been accepted. Obviously such acceptance is not a given, but working towards a goal like this can offer student researchers something to aim for. Their instructors could co-author these materials, even, so that everyone has skin in the game.</p>

<p>This model changes the shape of what collaborative education can look like: it’s duration and its results. You don’t need a whole fellowship year. You could, in a reasonably short amount of time, tinker and play, and produce a substantial blog post, an article pitch, or a Library Research Guide (more on that in a moment).</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide14.jpg" alt="Jarvis Quote Slide" />As Jeff Jarvis has said, “we need to move students up the education chain.” And trust me - the irony of quoting a piece titled “Lectures are Bullshit” during a lecture to you is not lost on me. But stay with me.</p>

<p>Collaborative writing projects on DH topics are flexible enough to fit the many contexts for the kind of educational work that we do. After all, no one needs or values the same outcomes, and these shared and individual goals need to be worked out in conversation with the students themselves early on. Articulating these desires in a frank, written, and collaborative mode early on (in the genre of <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/charter/">the project charter</a>), can help the program directors to better shape the work to fit the needs of the students. But I also want to suggest that collaborative writing projects can be useful end products as well as launching pads, as they can fit the shape of many careers. After all, students come to digital humanities for a variety of different reasons. Some might be aiming to bolster a research portfolio on the path to a traditional academic career. Others might be deeply concerned about the likelihood of attaining such a position and be looking for other career options. Others still might instead be colleagues interested in expanding their research portfolio or skillset but unable to commit to a whole year of work on top of their current obligations. Writing projects could speak to all these situations.</p>

<p>I see someone in charge of shaping graduate programs as needing to speak to these diverse needs. This person is both a steward of where students currently are – the goals and objectives they might currently have – as well as of where they might go – the potential lives they might (or might not!) lead. After all, graduate school, like undergraduate, is an enormously stressful time of personal and professional exploration. If we think simply about a student’s professional development as a process of finding a job, we overlook the real spaces in which help might be most desired. Frequently, those needs are the anxieties, stresses, and pressures of refashioning yourself as a professional. We should not be in the business of creating CV lines or providing lists of qualifications alone. We should focus on creating strong, well-adjusted professionals by developing ethical programs that guide them into the professional world by caring for them as people.</p>

<p>In the graduate context, this involves helping students deal with the academic job market in particular. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide15.jpg" alt="Rogers Slide" /> To me in its best form, this means helping students to look at their academic futures and see proliferating possibilities instead of a narrow and uncertain route to a single job, to paraphrase the work of Katina Rogers. A sprinkler rather than a pipeline, in her metaphor. As Rogers’s work, in particular, has shown, recent graduate students increasingly feel that, while they experienced strong expectations that they would continue in the professoriate, they received inadequate preparation for the many different careers they might actually go on to have. <a href="http://praxis.scholarslab.org">The Praxis Program</a> and the <a href="http://praxis-network.org/">Praxis Network</a> are good examples of how to position digital humanities education as answers to these issues. Fellowship opportunities like these must be robust enough that they can offer experiences and outcomes beyond the purely technical, so that a project manager from one fellowship year can graduate with an MA and go into industry in a similar role just as well-prepared as a PhD student aiming to be a developer might go on to something entirely different. And the people working these programs must be prepared for the messy labor of helping students to realize that these are satisfactory, laudable professional goals.</p>

<p>It should be clear that this sort of personal and professional support is the work of more than just one person. One of the strengths of a digital humanities center embedded in a library like this one at UVA is that fellows have the readymade potential to brush up against a variety of career options that become revealed when peaking outside of their disciplinary silos: digital humanities developers and project manager positions, sure, but also metadata specialists, archivists, and more. I think this kind of cross-pollination should be encouraged: library faculty and staff have a lot to offer student fellows and vice versa. Developing these relationships brings the fellows further into the kinds of the work done in the library and introduces them to careers that, while they might require further study to obtain, could be real options.</p>

<p>To my mind the best fellowship programs are those fully aware of their institutional context and those that both leverage and augment the resources around them as they are able. We have been working hard on this at W&amp;L. We are starting to institute a series of workshops led by the undergraduate fellows in consultation with the administrators of the fellowship program. The idea is that past fellows lead workshops for later cohorts on the technology they have learned, some of which we selectively open to the broader library faculty and staff. The process helps to solidify the student’s training – no better way to learn than to teach – but it also helps to expand the student community by retaining fellows as committed members. It also helps to fill out a student’s portfolio with a cv-ready line of teaching experience. This process also aims to build our own capacity within the library by distributing skills among a wider array of students, faculty, and staff. After all, student fellows and librarians have much they could learn from one another. I see the Head of Graduate Programs as facilitating such collaborations, as connecting the interested student with the engaged faculty/staff/librarian collaborator, inside their institution or beyond.</p>

<p>But we must not forget that we are asking students and junior faculty to do risky things by developing these new interests, by spending time and energy on digital projects, let alone presenting and writing on them in professional contexts. The biggest risk is that we ask them to do so without supporting them adequately. All the technical training in the world means little if that work is illegible and irrelevant to your colleagues or committee. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide16.jpg" alt="Fitzpatrick Slide" /> In the words of Kathleen Fitzpatrick, we ask these students to “do the risky thing,” but we must “make sure that someone’s got their back.” I see the Head of Graduate Programs as the key in coordinating, fostering, and providing such care.</p>

<p>Students and junior faculty need support – for technical implementation, sure – but they also need advocates – people who can vouch for the quality of their work and campaign on their behalf in the face of committees and faculty who might be otherwise unable to see the value of their work. Some of this can come from the library, from people able to put this work in the context of guidelines for the evaluation of digital scholarship. But some of this support and advocacy has to come from within their home departments. The question is really how to build up that support from the outside in. And that’s a long, slow process that occurs by making meaningful connections and through outreach programs. At W&amp;L, we have worked to develop an <a href="http://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/initiatives/incentive-grants/">incentive grant program</a>, where we incentivize faculty members who might be new to digital humanities or otherwise skeptical to experiment with incorporating a digital project into their course. The result is a slow burn – we get maybe one or two new faculty each term trying something out. That might seem small, but it’s something, particularly at a small liberal arts college. This kind of slow evangelizing is key in helping the work done by digital humanists to be legible to everyone. Students and junior faculty need advocates for their work in and out of the library and their home departments, and the person in this position is tasked with overseeing such outreach.</p>

<p>So, to return to the opening motif, lists of skillsets certainly have their place as we bring new people into the ever-expanding field: they’re necessary. They reflect a philosophy and a vision, and they’re the basis of growing real initiatives. But it’s the job of the Head of Graduate Programs to make sure that we never lose sight of the people and relationships behind them.</p>

<p>Foremost, then, I see the Head of Graduate Programs as someone who takes the lists, documents, and curricula that I have discussed and connects them to the people that serve them and that they are meant to speak to. This person is one who builds relationships, who navigates the prepositions of my title. <img src="/assets/images/job-talk-slides/slide17.jpg" alt="Title Slide Last" /> It’s the job of such a person to blast the boundary between “you’re in” and “you’re out” so that the tech-adverse or shy student can find a seat at the table. This is someone who makes sure that the work of the fellows is represented across institutions and in their own departments. This person makes sure the fellows are well positioned professionally. This person builds up people and embeds them to networks where they can flourish. Their job is never to forget what it’s like to be the person trying to learn. Their job is to hear “I’m not a tech person” and answer “not yet, but you could be! and I know just the people to help. Let’s learn together.”</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on a Year of DH Mentoring]]></title>
    <link href="http://walshbr.com/blog/dh-mentoring/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-04T09:13:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://walshbr.com/blog/dh-mentoring</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>[Crossposted on the <a href="http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/reflections-on-a-year-of-dh-mentoring/">Scholars’ Lab blog</a> and the <a href="http://digitalhumanities.wlu.edu/blog/2015/12/03/reflections-on-a-year-of-dh-mentoring/">Digital Humanities at Washington and Lee blog</a>]</em></p>

<p>This year I am working with <a href="http://scholarslab.org/people/eric-rochester/">Eric Rochester</a> in the <a href="http://scholarslab.org/">Scholars’ Lab</a> on a fellowship project that has me learning natural language processing (NLP), the application of computational methods to human languages. We’re adapting these techniques to study quotation marks in the novels of Virginia Woolf (read more about the project <a href="http://scholarslab.org/digital-humanities/virginia-woolf-natural-language-processing-and-the-quotation-mark/">here</a>). We actually started several months before this academic year began, and, as we close out another semester, I have been spending time thinking about just what has made it such an effective learning experience for me. I already had a technical background from my time in the Scholars’ Lab at the beginning of the process, but I had no experience with Python or NLP. Now I feel most comfortable with the former of any other programming language and familiar enough with the latter to experiment with it in my own work.</p>

<p>The general mode of proceeding has been this: depending on schedules and deadlines, we meet once or twice every two weeks. Between our meetings I would work as far and as much as I could, and the sessions would offer a space for Eric and me to talk about what I had done. The following are a handful of things we have done that, I think, have helped to create such an effective environment for learning new technical skills. Though they are particular to this study, I think they can be usefully extrapolated to apply to many other project-based courses of study in digital humanities. They are primarily written from the perspective of a student but with an eye to how and why the methods Eric used proved so effective for me.</p>

<p><strong>Let the Wheel Be Reinvented Before Sharing Shortcuts</strong></p>

<p>I came to Eric with a very small program adapted from Matt Jockers’s book on Text Analysis with R for Students of Literature that did little beyond count quotation marks and give some basic statistics. I was learning as I built the thing, so I was unaware that I was reinventing the wheel in many cases, rebuilding many protocols for dealing with commonly recognized problems that come from working with natural language. After working on my program and my approach to a degree of satisfaction, Eric pulled back the curtain to reveal that a commonly used python module, the Natural Language ToolKit <a href="http://www.nltk.org/">(NLTK)</a>, could address many of my issues and more. NLTK came as something of a revelation, and working inductively in this way gave me a great sense of the underlying problems the tools could address. By inventing my own way to read in a text, clean it to make its text uniformly readable by the computer, and breaking the whole piece into a series of words that could be analyzed, I understood the magic behind a couple lines of NLTK code that could do all that for me. The experience also helped me to recognize ways in which we would have to adapt NLTK for our own purposes as I worked through the book.</p>

<p><strong>Have a Plan, but Be Flexible</strong></p>

<p>After discussing NLTK and how it offered an easier way of doing the things that I wanted, Eric had me systematically work through the <a href="http://www.nltk.org/book/">NLTK book</a> for a few months. Our meetings took on the character of an independent study: the book set the syllabus, and I went through the first seven chapters at my own pace. Working from a book gave our meetings structure, but we were careful not to hew too closely to the material. Not all chapters were relevant to the project, and we cut sections of the book accordingly. We shaped the course of study to the intellectual questions rather than the other way around.</p>

<p><strong>Move from Theory to Practice / Textbook to Project</strong></p>

<p>As I worked through the book, I was able to recognize certain sections that felt most relevant to the Woolf work. Once I felt as though I had reached a critical mass, we switched from the book to the project itself and started working. I tend to learn from doing best, so the shift from theory to execution was a natural one. The quick and satisfying transition helped the work to feel productive right away: I was applying my new skills as I was still learning to feel comfortable with them. Where the initial months had more the feel of a traditional student-teacher interaction, the project-based approach we took up at this point felt more like a real and true collaboration. Eric and I would develop to-do items together, we would work alongside each other, and we would talk over the project together.</p>

<p><strong>Document Everything</strong></p>

<p>Between our meetings I would work as far and as much as I could, carefully noting places at which I encountered problems. In some cases, these were conceptual problems that needed clarifying, and these larger questions frequently found their way into separate notes. But my questions were frequently about what a particular line of code, a particular command or function, might be doing. In that case, I made comments directly in the code describing my confusion. I quickly found that these notes were as much for me as for Eric–I needed to get back in the frame of mind that led to the confusion in the first place, and copious notes helped remind me what the problem was. These notes offered a point of departure for our meetings: we always had a place to start, and we did so based on the work that I had done.</p>

<p><strong>Communicate in as Many Ways as Possible</strong></p>

<p>We met in person as much as possible, but we also used a variety of other platforms to keep things moving. Eric and I had all of our code on <a href="https://github.com/erochest/woolf">GitHub</a> so that we could share everything that we had each been working on and discuss things from a distance if necessary. Email, obviously, can do a lot, but I found the chat capabilities of the Scholars’ Lab’s IRC channel to be far better for this sort of work. If I hit a particular snag that would only require a couple minutes for Eric to answer, we could quickly work things out through a web chat. With Skype and Google Hangouts we could even share the code on the other person’s computer even from hundreds of miles away. All of these things meant that we could keep working around whatever life events happened to call us away.</p>

<p><strong>Recognize Spinning Wheels</strong></p>

<p>These multiple avenues of communication are especially important when teaching technical skills. Not all questions or problems are the same: students can work through some on their own, but others can take them days to troubleshoot. Some amount of frustration is a necessary part of learning, and I do think it’s necessary that students learn to confront technical problems on their own. But not all frustration is pedagogically productive. There comes a point when you have tried a dozen potential solutions and you feel as though you have hit a wall. An extra set of eyes can (and should) help. Eric and I talked constantly about how to recognize when it was time for me to ask for help, and low-impact channels of communication like IRC could allow him to give me quick fixes to what, to me at least, seemed like impossible problems. Software development is a collaborative process, and asking for help is an important skill for humanists to develop.</p>

<p><strong>In-person Meetings Can Take Many Forms</strong></p>

<p>When we met, Eric and I did a lot of different things. First, we would talk through my questions from the previous week. If I felt a particular section of code was clunky or poorly done, he would talk and walk me through rewriting the same piece in a more elegant form. We would often pair program, where Eric would write code while I watched, carefully stopping him each time I had a question about something he was doing. And we often took time to reflect on where the collaboration was going - what my end goal was as well as what my tasks before the next meeting would be. Any project has many pieces that could be dealt with at any time, and Eric was careful to give me solo tasks that he felt I could handle on my own, reserving more difficult tasks for times in which we would be able to work together. All of this is to say that any single hour we spent together was very different from the last. We constantly reinvented what the meetings looked like, which kept them fresh and pedagogically effective.</p>

<p>This is my best attempt to recreate my experience of working in such a close mentoring relationship with Eric. Obviously, the collaboration relies on an extremely low student-to-teacher ratio: I can imagine this same approach working very well for a handful of students, but this work required a lot of individual attention that would be hard to sustain for larger classes. One idea for scaling the process up might be to divide a course into groups, being training one, and then have students later in the process begin to mentor those who are just beginning. Doing so would preserve what I see as the main advantage of this approach: it helps to collapse the hierarchy between student and teacher and engage both in a common project. Learning takes place, but it does so in the context of common effort. I’d have to think more about how this mentorship model could be adapted to fit different scenarios. The work with Eric is ongoing, but it’s already been one of the most valuable learning experiences I have had.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
